BETH: It’s common for some
individuals on the autistic spectrum
to behave in challenging ways.
Once the reasons behind this are
known, and there usually is a reason
for behaviour that challenges, there
are ways that this can be managed to
the benefit of everyone concerned.
When individuals with autism can manage
their own behaviour, they can learn
how to get along better with others.
JOE: Some individuals with autism might
refuse or ignore requests from others
and behave in a way which is socially
inappropriate such as disrobing, showing
aggression or injuring themselves.
This behaviour may challenge the feelings
and thoughts of others they interact with.
When those who interact with individuals
with autism understand why they behave
this way, such as having trouble with
verbal and non-verbal communication and
the frustration it can cause, they are
more likely to respond more positively.
If they are aware of what might trigger
the individual with autism, they
can try to alleviate any stressors
which could develop into triggers
to behaviour that challenges others.
BETH: Challenging behaviour is in itself
not always a problem for an individual
with autism, as it can often be a way of
them gaining satisfaction and control over
a situation, however it is challenging
to those around them, as it does not
fit with what is recognised generally
as ‘normal’ or acceptable behaviour.
JOE: Sometime a particular person is
may become a target for behaviour that
challenges, it could be a peer, a family
member, a teacher or a support worker.
BETH: Whoever it is, it is important to
think about what the trigger might be.
It may be the clothes they wear
such as the pattern, texture or
colour, it may be their perfume is
overwhelming to the individual or
maybe the person is associated with
a distressing place or activity.
JOE: Maybe they don’t like the fact
that the person spends too much
time with others, in their eyes, as
they want them solely to themselves,
or they may simply clash with
the person for no obvious reason.
This can be remedied if the person
is a support worker as other people
could replace them but if it is a
family member it is more of a problem.